Okay, welcome everyone. Welcome back to 8225, which is also STS042, physics in the 20th
century. Let me start by asking just quickly, if there are any logistical questions, any
kind of course structure or other questions like that, we can try to clear up quickly
and then we'll jump into the first main lecture. In general, it's good to do the readings at
least to skim the more technical readings before the assigned class. So for today, that
was a brief excerpt from Maxwell's treatise on electricity magnetism, for example, at
a chapter from Bruce Hunt's book on the Maxwellians. So in general, it would be helpful if students
keep up with the readings because it's just going to snowball. Otherwise, some of the
readings, as you probably have noted with the Maxwell in particular, are pretty, they're
not exactly a page turning novel, right? Like what's going on with that? So I'm going to
be talking about what Maxwell thought he was doing, what some of Maxwell's contemporaries,
how they read that book in today's lecture. So for that, as a, so today might hopefully
we'll exemplify the kind of kind of use to make of readings like that as we go through
the kind of first worked example with Maxwell today. Other readings, as you'll see like the
chapter from Bruce Hunt for this week, are by physicists or historians or sociologists
or other more recent scholars, trying to help us make sense of that older work. And for
those, I think it does make sense to read them a bit more closely, what's the actual
argument the author is making? What are the kinds of evidence does the author bring to
bear? Because we'll work on together over the course of the semester is actually working
on your own written essays, your own analyses, where you will be will help you will build
up toward it. But you'll be working on articulating an argument, defending an argument evidence
and examples from various sources. So those, the readings that we would call a secondary
source readings by historians or more recent physicists or philosophers or sociologists
or journalists or whomever. Those are more like the kinds of writings we're going to
try to do ourselves over the course of the term. So I'd recommend, plus I think hopefully
they're interesting, I've chosen for you know, very carefully. So I do recommend you try
to read those a bit differently, let's say, than something like skimming over Maxwell's
treatise, which might look both pretty bland and weird and a little unusual given how we
do things today. So there are kind of different ways to read the different kinds of sources.
And I guess I hopefully today we'll actually give a bit of an example of that as we took
talk a little bit about that Maxwell reading throughout today. So that's the plan. And if
there's no other questions, I think we'll just jump right in. So I'm going to go ahead
and share screen. And hopefully you can see that first slide. So today we're going to start our kind
of journey in earnest. We're going to turn the clock back about 200 years and talk about some of
the leading natural philosophers and the leading people who are trying to understand the physical
world. And what did they think their job was? What were the settings in which they did it? What
were the conceptual tools they brought to bear? And we'll always be asked ourselves what looks
kind of similar and what looks really, really unfamiliar from our vantage point today. So
the discussion today has three main sections. We have a brief kind of warm up on physics then
and now just to try to prep us to put our minds back into the world of the early 19th century.
Then we'll spend a bit of time talking about Michael Faraday, who was one of the most widely
celebrated scientists or natural philosophers of his day. And we'll see some of the things that
he introduced during his rather unusual career. And then the last main section for today, we'll
talk about some of the folks who are a bit younger than Faraday, who kind of took up his mantle,
who tried to continue his line of work, but again, using some some different kinds of techniques
and tools. In this case, William Thompson and James Clark Maxwell. So that's our kind of goal
for today. So let's just pause and remember that we are entering a kind of, you know, imaginary
time capsule and going back, you know, about 200 years to start. So the assumptions that we might
bring in as physics students, as MIT students more generally, about how the world works about what
the job of a physicist is and so on, those won't map on perfectly well to some of these earlier
folks we start talking about. And I really I find that that's part of what's so fun for me about
working in the history of science is exactly those moments where things don't look so familiar, as
well as a continuity we can trace over time. So one of the biggest questions we might ask about
physics today is what's the world made of? What do we think as modern day scientists are the basic
building blocks out of which the world is made? If we were to conduct, you know, a survey of most
working physicists at MIT or really anywhere around the world at this point, we'd get an answer along
these lines. We would hear about something called the standard model of particle physics, which is
amazing and we'll actually talk a bit about the standard model later in this semester. It describes
the world is made up of a very small number of fundamental entities, elementary particles like
the quarks and electrons and tau mesons and neutrinos and even the long elusive Higgs boson.
There's a collection, not a very big collection of stuff out of which we think literally everything
else is made. We hear the physicists today talk about the tools that have been developed to try to
study interactions of those elementary bits of matter, how different particles can interact
with each other, can scatter off each other, can transmit the fundamental forces of nature
by exchanging certain kinds of particles in a vacuum. Depending on which physicists we ask,
we might get an earful, maybe more than we invited, saying that actually all those particles of
themselves really only the kind of the efflorescence of more fundamental entities called strings that
live in some abstract space. The point is we're going to get an answer like this about basically
particles exchanging particles in the vacuum. Now if we were to build our time machine, which I
sincerely hope we can complete soon, and we go back a hundred or little in 200 years to say talk
with leading natural researchers in Britain, and we told them this answer that physicists today said
the world has made of particles exchanging particles in a vacuum, they would have thought we
were really not with it. I like to think they would have shouted bollocks or at least something
maybe more colorful. Every single part of this modern answer would have looked extraordinarily
wrong-headed to the people that we're going to spend some time reading about and talking about
at the start of this term. And why is that important? I mean if we if we did this exercise with the
ancient Mayans or the medieval Turks or the Renaissance French we'd also expect some disagreement.
What I like about this is that we're turning the clock back not so far compared to the present day
and yet we already see a huge divergence in the answers as we'll see throughout today and
actually for several class sessions for the term, we use their equations. We still use, you know,
Maxwell's equations for example and a lot of the ideas that Michael Faraday introduced,
and yet what they thought those equations meant, what they thought they were describing about how
the world is made up, are almost, you know, 180 degrees opposite from how we start our investigations
today. So even though some parts have remained the same going over these 150 or 200 years to the
past, how we make sense of those ideas or those techniques have gone through a really quite amazing
change. So what do we think the world is made of? That's not a kind of static set of answers and we
see pretty dramatic change even over a relatively short span of history. There's another kind of
shift that we want to get our heads into, kind of attune ourselves to as well, and that concerns
who pursues the study of physics and in what kinds of settings, what institutions. So during the
first half of the 19th century, we'll start this class, people who worked on what we would call
physics, electricity, magnetism, optics, other phenomena, heat, they also worked on things that
we would call not physics, like chemistry or mathematics or astronomy, physiology, even beyond
that. For them, this was all kind of one field of study. It was often grouped under the term
natural philosophy rather than physics or chemistry or mathematics per se. In fact, the term for
a person who studied these things in English, the term we would call scientist, was actually only
invented in 1834. It's remarkably new as far as the English language goes. It was invented
after some of the developments we'll actually start talking about today. So even having the job
description scientist or the title is actually relatively new and what these particular kinds
of scientists that we would now call physicists, what they thought they should do, again, some pretty
broad changes compared to what we're used to today. Not only do they think their job description was
different than what we might imagine for ourselves, but where they did the work and what kinds of
settings or institutions, that was also pretty different merely 200 years ago, let alone much
further back in human history. So a lot of stuff we'll start by talking about today was not done
in schools or universities. They were done in separate institutes or academies and the key
thing is these were not places where students took classes to get degrees. There was a kind of
separation between kind of learning institutions. Universities existed throughout many parts of
the world, including Western Europe and the United States. Universities existed, but that was not
where people were doing what we would call scientific research. In fact, some of the most
prominent natural philosophers or leading physicists were not only not professors at
universities, some of them had never even attended university themselves. And that's true of the
first figure we'll look at today, Michael Farage. So there's a big shift toward a kind of placement
of this research that would look more familiar, things more like what we'd expect to see ourselves.
That shift begins in the middle of the 19th century, so more like 150 or 107 years ago,
rather than 200 years ago or more. There's a shift to where research in fields like physics
gets done more often than not by people who are professors in universities who also spend some
of the time teaching students, like what we are more used to today. That has a history,
it's actually relatively recent, and it has and it emerges really in the middle part of the 19th
century. So the overall theme of this very first kind of warm-up for the class is to kind of put
ourselves on guard. We shouldn't assume that our current sense of what's expected or normal or
familiar, either about how we choose to study the natural world, what concepts we use, let alone
how we think we should be pursuing that, what kinds of institutions or job descriptions. We
shouldn't expect that what's familiar to us today is just how people did things in the past,
and in fact we'll see some pretty dramatic changes over a relatively short span of time.
So let me pause there and ask them any questions, just on that early kind of warm-up.
Anyone have any thoughts or questions about that?
If not, then I'm going to press it on. Again, feel free to jump in on the chat if things come up.
Let's talk about this first figure I already mentioned, Michael Faraday. We're going to spend a
little time talking about Faraday. I think he's fascinating. So he became one of the most successful
and actually one of the most famous natural philosophers in his lifetime, in fact really
of the entire 19th century. He had a pretty remarkable personal story and I think we'll
also see he helps sort of make clear some of the larger social and institutional changes going on
as well. He helps us understand his own larger time period. Personally, he had this really
kind of inspiring rags to riches story. He was born into a rather poor family. He never attended
high school, let alone college or university. He was apprenticed to a book binder at age 13.
That means he literally left his family, moved in with his main tutor, and was apprenticed in a kind
of trade. So in that sense, his career path started out closer to what we might expect of
the Renaissance or even the Middle Ages into the modern period. It was a kind of time still of guilds
and of trade associations and his role, his way to make a living, was to learn the kind of manual
dexterity skills of being a book binder starting early on. He met the very famous chemist or natural
philosopher Humphrey Davy. When Davy gave a series of public lectures on natural philosophy at the
Royal Institution in London, and we'll talk a bit about the Royal Institution, it was not a university,
it was a place where research was done and public lectures were given. So Faraday was just mesmerized
by Davy's lectures. He actually took very careful notes on these public lectures. Faraday then bound
into a beautiful, very fancy book, and here's how we know he was so smart. He then gave that fancy
book to Davy as a gift, and I have a hint here of what you can do with that information. He basically
brought his way into a new kind of apprenticeship. Davy was very flattered and impressed by the kind
of manual skills, by the dexterity that Faraday had shown. So Davy hired Faraday for basically a
new kind of apprenticeship. Faraday had never attended high school or college. It wasn't that he was
trained in mathematical physics, quite the contrary. But Davy figured Faraday could do some new kinds
of manual dexterity skills in the laboratory as a laboratory assistant, a kind of continuation
of his bookbinder apprenticeship. So that's how Faraday enters what we would now call the world
of natural philosophy. So years and years go by, they work very closely for a long time. Davy
eventually steps down, he retires, and Faraday in fact became his successor, now the director of
this royal institution in London. So much like I mentioned a few moments ago, Faraday worked on
really a kind of mind-boggling array of topics, mind-boggling from our modern point of view,
quite kind of familiar to his own contemporaries. So he worked on what we would separately
classify as chemistry, optics, electricity, magnesium, electrolysis, and more. To Faraday,
these were all elements of a single unified approach to nature, and he was particularly
fascinated, even more than some of his contemporaries, with his inter-convertibility of forces.
How could electrical effects make physiological effects happen, like using electric shocks to
make a frog's leg jump? How could chemical effects be catalyzed by electric currents? So
the way that one kind of phenomenon or force could have effects in some other domain.
Now Faraday was partly inspired in this kind of inter-convertibility view
by his own religious backgrounds. I'm really very interested in work by a number of historians,
biographers of Faraday, who've tried to understand why Faraday took this kind of notion even further,
even more fervently, than many of his own contemporaries. And these other historians make
a pretty compelling case. Faraday belonged to a rather small religious minority in England.
He was a Protestant, but he was not an Anglican. He was not a member of the official Church of
England. He belonged to a small sect called the Sandamanians, Protestant, but not Anglican.
And the Sandamanians, even more than the standard Church of England at the time,
emphasized a underlying unity to all of nature. We're all part of one natural world,
and that people and things are somehow connected to each other. That was part of what the
Sandamanians themselves kind of believed and had a theological import for them. And there's a really
interesting parallel at the very least in some of the ways that Faraday had explored the natural
world as well. He became a beloved, very successful public lecturer. He continued the tradition that
Humphrey Davy had done at the Royal Institution, giving these very, very well attended so-called
Christmas lectures. These still continue from the Royal Institution to this day. Faraday would
really fill the lecture hall and give these dazzling spectacular demonstrations of electrical
effects and chemical change and all the rest. That's partly why he became so beloved and well
known in his lifetime. You can't quite see it in this engraving. It's hard to tell, but these were,
this really was the definition of popular. The tickets were not too expensive. That's partly how
very young and poor Faraday himself was able to attend as a child. It wasn't like attending, you
know, the fanciest opera performance in high elite London. There was a kind of, you wouldn't,
there'd be cheap seats. You can see how large the hall was. So there, the very nice, you know,
fancy seats then as now were expensive and tickets would go to the affluent and well to do.
But there really was what we today would call a kind of outreach. It was a real effort to reach
across several kind of social and economic classes, not all the way but broader than only
the very elite. And they became a really beloved kind of city institution within London. People
would come in from out of town to attend them. They became an annual tradition and Faraday
became especially beloved as a presenter in that tradition. So they really were reaching not only
people who had any interest in natural philosophy. It was really the kind of a way of showing a kind
of sophistication and a way for members of the so-called aspiring classes, meaning those who
weren't so well to do, to be able to participate in things that they saw the really elites doing.
So it really had a interesting kind of social cross-section to them. Historians have written
a lot of issues, that's not these public lectures. They really were talked about broadly,
covered in the in the broad sheet newspapers and all that. In this time period, the main
mechanisms were largely books. So even, even scientists like when we would call physicists
were mostly writing monographs and sometimes writing short articles for fellow specialists.
There were scientific journals, some of the earliest had been founded in England going back
to the 1660s, similar ones in other parts of Europe. But the real kind of transfer mechanisms
were often through monographs. That's partly why Maxwell's treatise that we'll talk about later
today became so widely known as influential. There were then these lectures. They were also
so-called itinerant lectures. People who made their whole living just giving popular lectures
on topics like electricity, town to town. So not just in London, but to the, to the outskirts and
likewise throughout provincial France and other places. So there were kind of popular lectures
in that sense. You can think of it almost like, like PBS television today, like Nova Specialists.
But for fellow specialists, there were just the start of professional meetings, the British
Association for the Advancement of Science. I'm having annual meetings of the sort that
will become so familiar for fellow specialists. Sometimes those will be covered in the national
newspapers. It was a hodgepodge. Some things would look familiar to us. Some things might seem a little,
a little more unusual. But Faraday wrote books and books and some articles, for example.
And certainly some of this would get into the curriculum for universities and we'll talk more
about that actually especially later today and in the next class session. But the way that kind of
fellow researchers interacted with fellow researchers, it was largely through books,
sometimes through journals and through these different kinds of lectures. Great, great questions.
I'm going to move on. These are great questions. I'll try to answer more than I don't get to
as we go further. But I want to get to one of the topics that was really, really high on Faraday's
list of most important, because this is really going to set our kind of agenda for several classes
to come. And that's what was called the ether, a presumptive, a hypothetical medium that pretty
much everyone that we're going to talk about, Faraday included, just assumed they kind of knew
they had an extremely strong confidence that this medium was filling all of space, filled every
nook and cranny of the universe. And it was this medium that filled everything that enabled various
processes to affect one another. That was the kind of interconvertibility of forces. Why did
electrical effects lead to magnetic effects? Because they're both ultimately effects of this
ether that connects everything. So what's the ether? Just during Faraday's own childhood,
another kind of amateur British naturalist named Thomas Young, building on some work by
French scholars from around the same time, right around the year 1800, had advanced a wave theory
of light. This is opposite actually to Isaac Newton's theory of light, who had a particle or
corpuscular theory. So Thomas Young, like some of the French scholars as well, suggested a whole
bunch of optical phenomena like interference, like reflection and refraction, could really
only be made sense of if light was a series of waves. And I'm sure you've seen this is a very
simple illustration. If two waves are perfectly in sync with each other, we'd say in phase,
you can get constructive interference, the peaks will become larger than either wave alone,
the trunks become deeper. Of course, if those two waves are exactly out of sync with each other,
if they're perfectly out of phase, you can get destructive interference and the resultant wave
will vanish altogether and sort of anything in between. So Young and others were convinced that
these interference phenomena kind of were natural indications that light is a wave phenomena. But
then the next question is, well, waves of what? Waves in what? Ocean waves are clearly waves of
water. Sound waves or compressions are waves in the atmosphere, in the air. What are waves of?
So they said, well, any wave we know about is a wave in some medium. There must be a medium
that carries these light waves. It was called the luminiferous ether, which is a very fancy word.
You can see how to parse it here. If you remember either Latin or Harry Potter, I find them equally
helpful. Think about the Lumos spell in Harry Potter. The lumini art just means light, referring to
light. Ferris means carrying, thinking like a ferris wheel. So the formal name of luminiferous
ether really just means the light carrying or the light bearing ether. This was the medium
in which light traveled, in which everything, all of the physical phenomena were immersed,
which is why these folks would never have said the stuff of the world is elementary particles
traveling in vacuum. There is no vacuum. Everything at root is filled with ether. That's where they
were starting from. So why would you need a medium for light? Again, even before around the same time
as Thomas Young in England, a number of French scholars had found that the speed of light, the
speed at which light waves travel depends on the medium in which they're traveling. In fact,
they're slower in water than in air. That's opposite, by the way, than sound waves. Sound waves travel
more quickly in a dense medium. That led to things like Snell's law, the whole set of knowledge
about refraction and how light behaves when it crosses from one type of medium to another.
You can characterize these media in terms of what became known as an index of refraction.
Everything about the behavior of these waves seemed to depend on the medium through which
they were traveling. There must be some baseline or reference medium, the ether,
with respect to which any of these deviations would then be measured. Water is one type of
medium, but even if you take all the water away and have an evacuated chamber,
you still have light waves traveling in the remaining ether. That was how they organized
these studies, or so much for light. What about other things like electricity and magnetism?
So again, during Faraday's early career, by this point, he was already kind of ensconced
to the Royal Institution, still working closely with people like Humphrey Davy,
there was a headline grabbing event not found in Britain, but actually nearby in Denmark.
So when another natural philosopher Hans Christian Orsted was giving a public lecture,
very much like at the Royal Institution, same kind of format. These were popular throughout.
Orsted was giving a public lecture and he accidentally discovered in the midst of his talk
something that he really didn't expect. He had an apparatus that looked a lot like this,
a kind of conducting coil, so there's a conducting wire, and he had nearby a compass,
so a magnetic needle. And he found that when current was flowing through the wire,
the needle would be deflected. He did not expect that at all, none of his audience expected that,
no one else expected that. Somehow that electric current, the flow of electricity,
could induce magnetic effects. It could change the behavior of that magnetic needle of the compass.
This became headline news if there had been 19th century Twitter, this would have broken Twitter,
hashtag the needle move, I'm sure. This was like literally whatever it was super exciting,
including people like Michael Faraday. This was for Faraday exactly this kind of
interconversion of forces that he was so interested, partly from his San Dominion faith,
partly because he was a natural philosopher of his time. So not only does he quickly
replicate Orsted's finding, he separately finds that he can get electric current to move a compass
needle. He then finds the inverse. He then does, as shown here, he takes a bar magnet
and starts moving it in a pattern near a conducting coil from which he can measure the
current as an ammeter attached. And he finds the inverse can happen as well, that a moving magnet,
a changing magnetic effect, can induce an electric current. So he's investigating induction, both
sort of electric currents inducing magnetic effects, magnetic fields or magnetic effects
inducing electric effects. And he wants to kind of keep track of this stuff. So he starts sketching
these helpful doodles that he calls lines of force. As far as Faraday was concerned, these were
lines of force to depict the underlying state of the ether. Remember, everything as far as he's
concerned is what's going on with the underlying ether. So it must be, he begins to reason with
these kind of pictorial aids, that the ether could be put under states of strain or tension. That's
if I have an electric charge that I place within the ether, it's going to have an effect and put
a kind of strain on the ether immediately around it. So he draws these lines of force emanating
either outward from positive electric charge or collapsing in toward a negative electric charge.
And then he begins using his sort of like middle school level mathematics. He'd had a little bit
of geometry before leaving formal schooling. And he puts that to work. He says he supposes,
what if a number of lines that come outwards from a positive charge is fixed and is proportional to
the amount of that electric charge. So a charge of say seven units would have seven of these lines
radiating outward, affecting the surrounding ether. A charge of 10 units would have 10 lines
radiating outward and so on. Then you can imagine what would happen if you surrounded that positive
charge with a kind of imaginary sphere at some distant radius. Then you can ask how many lines
per unit area will cross through that imagined sphere. The density of filled lines will fall
out. The lines are dispersing as you get further and further away from the electric charge. So the
density of filled lines, how many of those lines will intersect a kind of unit of that sphere
will fall off like one over r squared. You take the fixed number of lines, divide by the surface
area that you've surrounded that charge by. The area goes by like four pi r squared. So the density
should fall off like one over r squared. That was really exciting to Faraday because he had learned
from, again, from French scholars like Coulomb not too long before, really just in Faraday's own
childhood, that there was this Newton-like force of attraction or repulsion among electric charges.
We now call it Coulomb's law. That this magnitude of the force between two electric charges falls
off like one over the square, the distance, exactly as Faraday had kind of reasons toward
by thinking about state's attention in the ether and how that strain would be kind of dissipated
at more and more distance. So Faraday went on. Remember, he was so excited not only about one
topic like electricity, but also about magnetism. What if you plop a bar magnet down in the ether?
Then he could do that with these things like iron filings and trace out the kind of lines of
influence around the magnet, something you've probably done even as a child. And he realized
that he could make sense of this also in terms of lines of force, that these iron filings were
helping him map out the kind of magnetic effects, the strain that the bar magnet with its north and
south magnetic poles could do for the surrounding ether. What's really interesting here is that
Faraday starts to say that sometimes forces might not be transmitted only along the kind of straight
line shortest path between A and B. That was the sort of rule for all Newton-like forces. The
magnetic lines of force would bend. They'd curve. They would have these kind of looping paths.
And so maybe the magnetic force did not always go on shortest distance paths.
And more generally, Faraday starts saying, let's keep track of all these states of tension in the
ether. He introduces this notion of the field, something that physicists to this day use every
single day of our careers. We now call it field theory. It largely comes as being introduced
by Faraday as he tries to make sense of with kind of convenient mnemonic devices, these states of
strain in the ether. So the electric and magnetic fields, as far as Faraday was concerned, were
simply ways of characterizing the local state of the ether as represented by these kind of lines
of force. What were the stresses and strains at that spot in the ether? How do they change if
they go to this spot? How do they change if that one spot over time? This is what he says is the
notion of a field. It's just shorthand for the state of the underlying ether. But is that real?
Might still wonder, is the ether just a helpful thing to think about or did Faraday and his colleagues
think he was really part of the world? And it was unambiguously for them part of the world,
not just convenient to think about, but really the stuff from which the world was made. And we'll
talk about this in some more detail over coming class sessions. Faraday thought he found like the
golden proof in 1845, but now he was much more senior researcher. How could you demonstrate
the ether was real? Well, let's study the interaction in magnetic fields and the behavior of light,
in particular polarized light. This is now known as the Faraday effect or the Faraday rotation.
It's one of these things that's literally still in our textbooks. We use it all the time. It comes
from Faraday's efforts to prove to himself and his colleagues that we are all immersed in this
elastic bendable ether. So Faraday and his peers, the idea was the following, that if you put the
ether under local strain by putting a local magnetic field in some region of space, that
magnetic field will have a kind of twisting or curling effect, a kind of torsion on the underlying
ether. And then this light wave is traveling through this kind of deformed local bit of the
ether. So its behavior will change in a particular what's called the plane of polarization. The
direction in which its wave is waving will rotate. There'll be some angle shown here is the angle beta.
So if the field starts out, the wave starts out waving in one direction, it will literally
rotate it by some angle. The amount of rotation depends on the strength of the field and the
distance through which this ether is under tension. This is not just a good idea for 1845.
It's how we make sense of the world today, minus the ether part. But it comes from trying to figure
out is the ether real. Just last year I had fun working with a really terrific Europe student,
some of you might know Max Doshner, he and my friend Joe Formaggio in physics. We use this exact
same phenomenon that an external magnetic field will rotate the plane of polarization of light,
not to talk about the ether but as a way to jam quantum encryption indefinitely. So in the sort
of hyper-modern physics of the moment, we're still going back to Faraday rotation and yet
Faraday thought this was a way of characterizing the ether. I just love that. We're going to see many
examples of that throughout the class. Let me wrap up the Faraday part. I'll pause again for some more
questions. So Faraday as we've seen worked on a variety of phenomena, what we would call separately
chemistry and optics, electrolysis, even physiology, let alone electricity and magnetism. He was
especially interested in the inter-convertibility of forces, partly the compelling case of the maid,
this kind of resonance, especially closely with his sort of religious minority views,
his Sandamanian views, and that there was this kind of underlying unity of nature. Faraday was
never trained in advanced mathematics. He had really just the rudiments of this kind of pictorial
geometry like we saw with the kind of lines of force. He was an apprentice tinkerer. He had
tremendous manual dexterity skills and also great cleverness. He became this leading experimentalist
based on not formal training at a university, but being kind of apprenticed as a book binder and then
essentially apprenticed as Humphrey Davis assistant at the Royal Institution, not at a university.
He introduces these things which we still use to this day like lines of force and then fields.
For Faraday, these are ways of characterizing the one big prize of natural studies, meaning the ether,
the medium within which all these things unfolded, and the reason as far as Faraday was concerned,
why there could be this inter-convertibility and unity. So in place of Newtonian action at a distance
that somehow one object could instantaneously affect or exert a force on another one, Faraday
starts explaining all physical phenomena. He has the ambition to explain everything in terms of these
local fields. There's a local disturbance here at position x equals one and it can convey effects
to its nearest neighbors point by point. So you have to study how these fields change over time
and spread out through space. Everything is now meant to be local fields, not action at a distance.
Let me pause there again and ask me any questions. See at least one more item in the chat.
Any questions on the Faraday material?
Very good. So it was common to attend the public science lectures. In fact, it was seen as a way
of being kind of elegant. Again, it does a really fascinating work on the kind of social class
emulation going on, especially heightened as you might know in in Britain in this time period.
So to be considered a kind of fashionable lady in the terminology today, one had to show or at
least feign interests in a range of topics, one of which was these kind of, you know, elegant
demonstrations of the glories of the world. For many people this, by the way, had a kind of overt
religious significance, a kind of natural theology. Not for everyone, but for many in this period,
the idea was that learning about how electric shocks make frogs, frogs legs twitch, or how
magnetic bar magnet can change, can induce electric current. These are ways of kind of
revealing the glory of God's creation, as many people argued at the time. So it was seen as
actually a function of kind of moral or spiritual uplift. And therefore, again, according to the
kind of assumptions that we might say, prejudice is the time, therefore, all the more important for
young women to be exposed to this was a thinking of the time with their kind of tender moral souls
that needed special care, again, to speak in their idiom, not my own. So there actually was a great
encouragement for women to attend these public lectures, not, not as you might expect, to move
into the laboratory, not to do the work. That was an almost uniquely male enclave in this period,
certainly in the Royal Institution. But to be sort of exposed, to be part of the broader kind of
polite discussions, it was one way of showing that you were, you know, how to kind of appropriate
upbringing. And again, there's lots of cool stuff. I'd be glad to talk more about that or send some
references to Marie. The short answer was, yes, to attend the Christmas Lectures at Royal Institute,
that was an awesome thing to, you know, bring your daughter to. But, but at the time, and
there's something we'll see change rather slowly, but change over time throughout the semester.
At that time, it was not something that was seen as a kind of acceptable or appropriate day job or
a career path. So that was a very, very clear gender disparity, but a great openness to have
women participate in that limited way in the kind of public lectures. So very good question. We'll
come back to that, that theme quite a lot. Great questions. Oh, that's so good. So we'll come to
actually, we'll come to some of that in his very next unit right now. So, so partly I'll just punt.
But the short answer is there was a growing recognition in just this time period among
many influential government leaders, not only in Britain, in many parts of Europe, in fact,
many parts of the world, China and Japan, certainly North America, a growing recognition by, by this,
during this exact time period, that many nation states would benefit from investing in what we
would now call science and technology or science and engineering. So there certainly were hot button
issues, then as now, natural evolution, Darwin's theory of evolution, which comes just around this
time, first published in 1859. That becomes yet another flashpoint for tension and controversy.
But for a lot of this work, and what we would now call the physical science is,
as we'll see, there was actually a kind of investment, a new kind of priority in a lot of
this work, not across the board, not without its own hiccups, we'll come to that. But it was actually
a turning point in, in a new kind of investment, partly because many of these places were undergoing
their own kind of nation based industrial development. And we'll see that actually even more
explicitly in the next class, some of it today with Maxwell. And in the next semester was a great
question. It's a theme we'll trace throughout the semester. But even in in Faraday's own lifetime,
that was beginning to change into a more kind of a higher priority and investment in exactly
these topics. Great question. Any others? Should we, should we press on?
These are great. So keep in common. These are great historical questions to help us think about,
like, what was different back then? What might have been similar? So we're going to keep that kind
of back and forth in mind as we enter now just the last part for today's class. And we'll talk
about William Thompson and James Clark Maxwell. So as, as, as we saw these briefly, Faraday had
very little formal training in mathematics and he used very little in his own studies,
his very voluminous studies. And that's not surprising given what we know about his own
early childhood in education. There's a really remarkable shift, one that I still find unbelievably
fascinating. So we're going to spend quite a bit of time talking about it today and next class as well.
This amazing shift that begins really late in Faraday's own lifetime in the middle decades
of the 19th century. It doesn't only happen in Britain. We're going to look at it because it's
especially kind of dramatic or kind of blown out of proportion, we might say, in Britain at places
like Cambridge University. It's happening also in places like France and other parts of the world,
even beyond Europe. But, but Cambridge in Britain gives us like the kind of capstone picture that
and it's almost like pure essence. So there's a real sea change going on between Faraday's early
life and even the later years of his own career in, in the way that people would try to approach
national phenomena like electricity and activism. Two kind of exemplars, two examples of that shift
are names that might be familiar to many of you. And we'll spend a little time today talking about
some of their work. William Thompson, who is later known as Lord Kelvin, that's the same Kelvin from
the Kelvin temperature scale, absolute temperature familiar to you and other many other things.
So Thompson on one hand and James Clark, Max on the other. Again, I'm sure Max or a familiar name,
things like Maxwell equations and all the rest. So these two folks were about two generations
younger than Faraday. They were coming of age when Faraday was already a well known natural
philosopher. They pick up on Faraday's work. They were avid readers of Faraday's books, often
monographs, not just as articles. And they began to translate it into a very powerful mathematical
formalism of the sorts that Faraday had had no inkling of whatsoever. Turns out both Thompson
and Maxwell were born in Scotland. They were not from London or the immediate English surroundings.
They were both Scottish born. They both moved to Cambridge for their formal university training
in the middle decades of the 19th century. So both Thompson and Maxwell became deeply
involved coming to exactly the question that was raised just in that last question period.
They became deeply involved with what we might call kind of engineering aspects or applications
of natural philosophy all around the physics of the ether. They both had very long illustrious careers
not only when they were university students. They were pursuing these very fancy sophisticated
mathematical kind of formal mathematical approaches to electricity, magnetism, and the
physics of the ether, not only for the sake of pure mathematics. As we'll see, they were deeply
involved in very practical ways with things that governments wanted to pay for, like telegraphy
and other practical electrotechnical devices. So among the most important in their own careers
was indeed telegraphy. So as you know, Britain then as now was an island, it's still an island.
Back then it had lots and lots of colonies. That's what's changed. It was a period of still rapid
acceleration of the British colonial adventure. So distant outposts or so-called possessions,
territorial possessions, really all around the world. Again, many of you might recall the old quip
that the sun never sets on the British Empire. In that time period, there were colonial holdings
or territories that spanned really the entire globe. So at any given time of day, the sun was
shining on some British outpost. So what do you need if you're going to try to administer a world
spanning empire? You need ways to have efficient communication. And that was an enormous impetus
for things like telegraphy. Even with some of the former colonies like the United States or Canada,
some kind of formal colonial holdings, there was still an effort in this same period, the middle
decades of the 19th century, to have efficient long-distance communication for things like commerce
and diplomacy. So there were all kinds of reasons why electromechanical investigations were given
a very high priority in Britain in this time period. So we get a taste of, here's our first
quotation from that little bit of the Maxwell that I designed. Maxwell published this voluminous
treatise, a two-volume treatise in 1873. The two volumes together run to about 900 pages. It makes
for fun beach reading. But in the very opening of the preface, we get this really interesting
observation. He tells us partly why anyone should read this book. And he says here,
the important applications of electromagnetism to telegraphy have reacted on pure science by giving
a commercial value, and indeed a governmental diplomatic value, to accurate electrical measurements
and by affording to electricians, let's say experts in the field, the use of apparatus on a scale
which greatly transcends that of any ordinary laboratory. They're getting huge investments
to conduct very large investigations with very elaborate apparatus. The consequences of this
demand, this sort of government and commercial private interest demand for electrical knowledge
and of these experimental opportunities for acquiring that knowledge have already been
very great, both in stimulating the energies of advanced electricians and then diffusing among
practical men a degree of accurate knowledge which is likely to conduce to the general scientific
progress of the whole engineering profession. P.S. by my 900-page book is literally worth
something. That's what he's announcing in the opening pages of his treatise. So let's go a little
into some somehow William Thompson and James Clark Maxwell start treating Faraday's kind of
intellectual legacy. So Thompson began reading Faraday's books as well as some articles as an
undergraduate. Thompson was still, you know, basically 18 and 19 years old at Cambridge
when he starts devouring Faraday's work or continues to do so. He began to realize that he
could put Faraday's work, he could kind of translate it on the one hand, and also Newton's work on
mechanics within the same mathematical structure. This was the stuff that only in the middle decades
of the 19th century was what university students at Cambridge like William Thompson began to really
be immersed in. We'll talk much more about that in the next lecture. So we realized that you could
make this bridge, you could treat all these disparate phenomena within electricity and separately
all these disparate phenomena within Newton's mechanics, blocks sliding down planes, the attraction
of gravity, introduce one similar mathematical construct, the potential, a scalar potential,
which is often just labeled by the Greek letter phi. If this is brand new to you, don't worry,
if it's very familiar to you, great. The idea is that a scalar function, a scalar field like this
potential, it has values at every point in space, those values can change over time, but it doesn't
have direction, it has no, it only has magnitude. You can think of making a kind of representing
the temperature in the room at every location in space, and then tracking how those temperature
readings change over time at each location in space, that's a scalar function. Temperature is
scalar, it has magnitude, but not direction, that's hopefully review. Other things like these fields
that Faraday introduced for electricity magnetism, those have direction as well as magnitude,
those are vector quantities. Well, as Thompson was learning to just devour in his undergraduate
studies, you could create a vector quantity by taking kind of rates of change of a scalar
quantity, what we'd now call the gradient. So the gradient, often with this upside down triangle,
the gradient of a scalar function gives a vector function, and in particular,
one could represent these vector field like quantities of either electricity or gravitation
by first writing down a simpler mathematical object, the scalar function, scalar potential.
So he first reviews what had already been worked out by a bunch of 18th century savant
throughout France, French scholars throughout the 1700s, downstream from Newton himself.
They had really translated Newton's own work into this language of
directional quantities like fields, like forces in the gravitational field,
and then introduced this simplifying mathematical structure of a scalar potential.
And then you could study not just how the field is related to changes in that scalar function,
the gradient, you could see how the field would divert the divergence of that field
related to where the stuff is, the density of sources of gravitation, like the mass density.
This was basically a translation, re-translation of Newton's work from the 1680s,
translated into this more modern language throughout the 1700s by the French scholars
of direction filled vector quantities being related to derivatives to rates of change of
simpler scalar quantities. That was literally textbook stuff. That's what Thompson's learning
as an undergraduate. It's not Thompson, not those French folks in this case,
who says, can we make a one-for-one map? He's absorbing this cool Faraday stuff. He says,
what if we represent an electric field as the state of strain in the ether exactly as Faraday
had begun kind of groping toward pictorially? There's electrical forces to be forces related
to an electrical field, the state of disturbance of the ether. Sorry, how's that? Sorry, gang.
Okay. You can then relate the electric field, again, to rates of change of a simpler quantity,
a scalar potential, exactly analogous to the gravitational case. You can then ask how the
electric field is diverging throughout space and time, like those lines of force getting more and
more spread out from each other in Faraday's simple pictures. And that's related to where
the stuff is, to the sources of this electrical disturbance, the charge density, how many
electrical charged objects are distributed throughout space per unit volume, say. So,
he makes a one-to-one map. And he says, there's really this precise mathematical analogy
between electrical phenomena and mechanics, like Newton's laws, and the mapping is done by this
a little bit more formal, more fancy mathematics. So far, that's not so shocking. Thompson was
among the first to take this textbook side and start doing new things with it with the Faraday
cool E&M stuff. Within one year of when Faraday introduced what we now call Faraday rotation,
remember that thing about the external magnetic field rotating the plane of polarization for light?
Thompson does the same thing. He says, oh, good. Faraday has some new cool stuff. Let me put that
through my very fancy university mathematics. So now, he's still an undergraduate. Thompson is now
making brand new stuff, not just rewriting the known regularities among electrical phenomena,
but in fact, formalizing the brand new stuff, like Faraday rotation. He introduces a new kind
of mathematical object, the vector potential. That was not known even to the French savant.
We still call it the vector potential A. And he introduces a new operator, a new way of manipulating
that quantity, which we call the curl. Thompson events curl as an undergraduate. Just let that
sink in for a second. So, you know, the new semester's early, you all can invent all kinds
of new math before, let's say, November. Thompson's literally doing this like for fun on the weekends
because he can't get enough math. So, he introduces a vector potential and this curl because as Faraday
had kind of intuited, the effect of a magnetic field on the surrounding aether was kind of turning
or twisting strain, unlike the kind of straight line strain of an electric field. And so,
Thompson wanted to kind of formalize what that curl, what that twisting torsion would be like
as a different kind of strain in the aether. And he formalizes this new operator, which we now
know and love and use every single day. It comes out of Thompson trying to treat mathematically
formally what he was still learning very actively from people like Faraday. Pretty amazing.
So, far following Faraday's lead, Thompson begins to interpret this
mathematical result mechanically. Remember, we saw that one-to-one bridge between the kind of
Newton mechanic stuff and the electricity stuff. He says, if the same mathematics applies, maybe
it's the same physical explanation undergirding all of it. The aether, he'd learned from people
like Michael Faraday and others, the aether seemed to be this elastic physical medium. It was literally
a kind of stuff spread out everywhere and that medium could be put under local states of tension
or strain with twist, with directional properties described by these vectors. So, these new mathematical
techniques like Curl could quantify this physical mechanical medium's response to pressures like
electric and magnetic fields. He really took that to heart in a famous set of public lectures,
much like these London ones. He actually came to Baltimore in the United States and gave very,
very well attended popular lectures for in Baltimore. Thompson basically tried to give his
audience a feel for what these kind of experts were doing. This is a direct quotation. So, again,
people in their fancy opera gloves, like Out for Night in the Town, do you hear the great Lord
Kelvin by this point, the great ennobled Lord Kelvin described about the latest advances.
And he tells this fancy audience, stick your hand in a bowl of jelly, okay, and see how it
wiggles and vibrates as you move your hand around. That's what it was to do physics because the jelly
is just like this elastic aether. It's everywhere and the job of super smart ambitious people like
William Thompson was to quantify the wiggles and vibrations of that aether much as you would
if you disturbed this pot of jelly. I love that. This becomes known as a mechanical worldview.
If the mathematics was the same, make this one-to-one mathematical map, then maybe you could model
electromagnetism on literally a mechanical model. You have an elastic stuff under states of strain
with directional properties. And if the models reproduce all the relevant phenomena like Coulomb's
law and all the rest, all the electromagnetic phenomena, then maybe these aren't only analogies
or models. Maybe aether really was merely a mechanical system just like that jar of jam.
So it becomes a mechanical worldview. All of the things of the world are to be understood on the
mechanical kind of vibrations or responses of this space-filling aether. Last part, then I'll
pause for more questions. We're almost done. We're going to turn to Thompson's slightly younger
colleague James Clark-Maxwell. I mentioned they had a similar upbringing a couple years apart,
both Scottish, both come to Cambridge for their undergraduate studies.
Maxwell was a couple years younger. I don't think they actually overlapped in Cambridge. They came
to know each other later. Maxwell liked Thompson, he becomes steeped in his new Cambridge mathematical
training. We'll talk a lot more about the Cambridge training in the next class. And Maxwell develops
further analogies between these electromagnetic kind of aether-based systems and mechanical
systems. Here's a famous example. And this, by the way, you get some more description of this in
that chapter by Bruce Hunt in the reading for today. So the model, the effects of a magnetic field
on the aether, Maxwell imagines this elaborate system. Basically, it's like a contraption of like
pulleys and conveyor belts and gears. We don't have to worry about the detail so much.
The ambition is what I want to convey. That there's a physical model of an actual system,
a mechanical system of gears, levers, and straps that he thinks is what's really going on in the
aether when we do things like put a little patch of the aether under local strain from a magnetic
field. So between these kind of vortices as depicted here are these idle wheels, wheels that
sort of stay in place but can change the rate at which they turn. They really like these conveyor
belts. If an external force changed the rate at which one of these vortices was spinning,
you could change it by imposing one of these external fields like a magnetic field. You change
the rate at which this kind of unit cell is spinning. That changes the rate at which the
immediately nearest neighbors are going to be behaving. It's all this faraday field idea of
local neighbor to local neighbor, not action at a distance. So this unit cell starts to change
its rate of rotation. That changes the speed at which these intervening, these so-called idle
wheels spin. That then changes the rate at which they're nearest neighbors in because they're
literally connected. So it's all local effects. So all effects are local and the way that a
magnetic disturbance affects something over there is by these local effects propagating
through the medium in this kind of gears and straps conveyor belt sort of way. And again,
he gives us hints about this in the even in the brief excerpt from Axel's treatise that I assigned
for today. So he talks about how the action of one electrical system on another is affected
not by direct action at a distance, not the way Newton had said, but rather by means of a
distribution of stress in this medium, this elastic medium or the ether, extending continuously
throughout space. Likewise, he says a few pages later in the excerpt, the distribution of stress
in this medium, this ether, is precisely that to which faraday was led in his investigation of
induction of the fact that a moving magnet can induce electrical effects like an electric current.
At every point of the medium, there's a state of stress. Every part of the ether is under some
kind of stress, such that there's tension along the lines of force, pressure at right angles. He's
really building a mechanical model, almost sometimes a kind of hydrostatic one, other ones more likely
gears of a factory. This became how the Maxwellians, not just Maxwell, but even his nearest followers
and students and kind of protégés, that's what they thought it was to study the natural world,
to build more and more kind of articulated mechanical models of the ether with which they
could model and even predict more and more features of natural worlds like electromagnetic effects.
So one of his acolytes, Oliver Lodge, himself went on to a very, very distinguished career
in physics himself. He wrote a book a few years later, the Maxwell's treatise called
The Modern Views of Electricity, and it was all about this sort of Maxwellian approach within
this mechanical worldview to account for states of strain and ether using this kind of much more
articulated mapping, the fancy math that people like Thompson, Maxwell, and soon the whole Cambridge
group would articulate. Well, this didn't impress everyone. I love this book review. This is the
nastiest book review for a long, long time. Here's a review by the French mathematical
physicist Pierre Duem, reviewing Oliver Lodge's book, this sort of Maxwellian book. Duem hopes
he would like it. He also was very interested in electricism, but he just sniffs in this wonderful
sneering French way to wear the quoting. Duem says, here is a book intended to expound the modern
theories of electricity. In it, there are nothing but strings which move around pulleys,
which roll around drums, which go through pearl beads, which carry weights, and tubes which pump
water while others swell and contract. Toothed wheels are geared to one another, engage hooks.
This is the real kicker. We thought we were entering the tranquil and neatly ordered abode of reason,
but we find ourselves in a factory. This was not high praise. He was like, I thought I was going
to learn something edifying for my soul. Instead, this is literally low class stuff. This is the
most obnoxious takedown book of you that I could think of. This Maxwellian British approach doesn't
please everyone, and yet, as we'll see in the last little bit, they're starting to make some pretty
remarkable strides nonetheless. Last little bit, then we'll pause for questions. Last part for Max.
While working out this sort of mechanical model, how would local disturbances propagate
through this elastic medium of the ether? Maxwell starts putting in some quantitative
values for the way to characterize the kind of response of the ether. These are really like
spring constants. How stretchy is the ether, or how much stretchiness or tension do you get
sort of per unit applied external field? When we apply an external electric field to this part
of the ether, how much does the tension change or likewise the magnetic field? So we like spring
constants, analogous. And that's what he and his colleagues are measuring in their local laboratories
in studying. Then he goes back to these mechanical models to ask how quickly would a mechanical
disturbance begin to propagate within this mechanical ether? And he finds, really to his
surprise, he didn't see it coming, these disturbances in the ether, the moment by moment local effects
would move at a speed he already knew very well, the speed of light. Here's a direct quotation
in this very famous paper from 1865. And he says, the velocity of transverse undulations
in our hypothetical medium, I just love that phrase, transverse undulations in our hypothetical
medium, meaning the speed at which these waves of ether are traveling, that speed agrees so
exactly with the velocity of light that's calculated from optical experiments and actually mostly
astronomical tests, that we can scarcely avoid the inference that light consists of the transverse
undulations of the same medium, the ether, which is the cause of electric and magnetic
phenomena. Translated into how we might say it today, light waves were literally nothing,
but traveling disturbances of electric and magnetic fields within this light bearing
all pervasive ether. He gets that he gets this unification of electricity, magnetism and optics
by thinking very, very hard and very quantitatively about the mechanical response of this all
pervasive ether. So let me wrap up, then I'll pause, I see a bunch of comments coming up in the
chat, so I want to make sure you time to chat. So let me just wrap up and then we'll get to
discussion. Leading natural philosophers of the 19th century were really quite convinced and they
had very good reasons that the world has made up just different kinds of stuff than how our
contemporaries would answer that question, that opening question, what's the world made of?
The folks back then, world-leading, rightly celebrated scholars, Faraday, Thompson, Maxwell,
and for that matter, people like Pierre du Emond and his contemporaries as well,
they were convinced that the world was not made of elementary particles that skitter around a
vacuum, but rather there was no vacuum and particles were a kind of afterthought, we'll come back to
that next class, that the world is filled with this elastic physical medium, the ether, and
everything that matters is a response that ether to various kinds of mechanical disturbances,
as Lord Kelvin says, stick your hand in a bowl of jelly, see how it works, that's what the world has
made of. Up until the middle decades of the 19th century, many leading highly accomplished and
very influential natural philosophers like Michael Faraday could enter research careers
based on this apprenticeship model closer to the Middle Ages or the Renaissance than to today.
They often worked in sort of institutes which had no formal teaching function,
they were not for the most part based at universities, that's what begins to change
in the middle decades of the 19th century. So Faraday, Thompson, and Maxwell in their own
different ways pursued these analogies between this light-bearing or luminiferous ether and
mechanical systems. Faraday with his rather rudimentary geometrical arguments and his very
clever kind of pictorial aids, Thompson and Maxwell with his increasingly sophisticated
mathematics, we'll look at that some more next time. They all became convinced of what became
called a mechanical worldview. The electromagnetic effects were literally nothing but mechanical
effects, mechanical effects on this all-pervasive ether, moreover this is the birth of what we
now call field physics, local causes yield local effects, there's no action at a distance
unlike Newton's description of gravity. A can affect B but it'll take some time for the
effects to propagate and certain kinds of propagating effects like these electric and
magnetic transverse undulations will show up as nothing other than what we call light.
Let me stop sharing the screen there, open it up for questions, there's a huge set in the chat,
I might like I think I'll get won't get to them all today.
Great, great question, thank you. So there was a spectrum even among what we now
call the Maxwellians, they didn't all have you know exact same ideas or they shared a lot.
And so indeed some of them wondered is this a useful analogy and if so should we nonetheless
keep pursuing it, see what we get out of it. Others were convinced that it's more than it's
not merely an analogy, it's a helpful analogy precisely because of some deeper similarity
and individuals used change over time and the whole group would have a kind of
let's say evolving center of gravity. They were more like each other in the kind of Cambridge
scene than like say the French or the Germans or indeed communities further afield as we'll look at.
So I don't want to make it sound like they were all kind of like exactly had the same notion,
they were pretty similar compared to as we'll see actually we'll see a really interesting
contrast next class I think interesting with some leading scholars within the German states.
So there there was maybe the strongest contrast, but you're right that some of these even within
Cambridge are the kind of close Maxwellian colleagues, they were all delighted to pursue the
mathematical analogies and they were getting trained in this very, very elaborate mathematical
machinery as we'll talk more about next time. They shared that and they were impressed by what
the analogies would bring them either to explain something or to prompt new questions to then
try to go investigate the laboratory. It was a productive set of analogies. That was already
what they agreed on. Some then said it's not just analogy, the world is filled with jelly
effectively. It's a great question. It looks like Julia has very kind of compiled a bunch of
questions for me. Let me answer some that Julia has private chatted to me and if I miss some others
we have time for some more. So someone asks by way Julia if university and research institutions
were separated at the time who used to teach at the universities oh very good. People would teach
at the universities who had gone to universities so self-replicating. Now that's still true today,
but we've achieved a kind of monopoly whereas back then it wasn't such a monopoly. That is to say
people who would teach at universities had indeed been trained like William Thompson or James Clark
Maxwell by their own students and in fact we'll talk quite a bit about this in the next class and
something that I find really interesting and that was still separated from people who could enter
really elaborately amazingly prestigious careers like Michael Faraday or even Thomas Young before
him or Hans Christian Erstedt or many other names we counted today without going through that kind
of formal university setting. So the kind of apprenticeship model like get your hands dirty
on effectively a kind of elaborate internship and just like never leave that was still a viable
path in to conduct really world-class cutting-edge research. Then you'd often write your monograph,
your whole book about it, maybe deliver some fancy lectures, maybe some of the scholars at the
university would be interested and maybe write a textbook and maybe lecture on it in their classes
but they were kind of they were separated. The separation begins to be reduced starting in the
roughly 1850, 1840s, 1850s and they become much, much closer associated not automatically, not
without sort of some switches back and forth but the trend really sets in starting in the middle
of the 19th century. Again we'll look at that a bit more directly next time. Very good question.
So another question is why do we go from the convention used in Maxwell of denoting the
potential as Psy to now using it Phi? Oh very good, are they different? No, they're not different. So
I guess I skipped ahead to the modern. I showed my prejudices in my slides here,
just using the Greek letter Phi for potential. The short answer is I don't know what that particular
letter changed. What I do know and we'll talk about again next time is that as you had a taste
of again in the reader today, Maxwell was not using any of this fancy pants vector stuff. Maxwell
was writing everything out in explicit Cartesian coordinates. That's probably why I joke why his
book was 900 pages. Like if he just used vectors, I think it would have been a 20 page pamphlet,
you know, we'd be done. And so I talk a lot about that actually in the coming class. So the particular
question, how did Psy become Phi? It's interesting and I actually don't know. But the larger question
about Maxwell's notation and in particular how it could become so valuable for people like us
when he writes these incredibly clunky pain-in-the-buck kinds of things is probably why I gave you
those excerpts from his reader, from his treatise. It doesn't look just like, you know, our favorite
textbooks today, even when we're using quote-unquote his equations. So it's a great question. The
conventions actually show a lot of interesting stuff, even the particular question about Psy-Phi,
I admit I don't know. Regarding the wheels, pulleys as analogies for physical reality,
how is continuous rotational symmetry of the physics explained? Oh, that's interesting.
I think the idea, oh, that's good. Yeah, that's good. So I think they adjusted toward it by those
like molecular vortices. That's a kind of two-dimensional slice. And they certainly were
things like spheres. So a lot of it, they talked about ball bearings. They actually have spherical
symmetry. And so they constructed even more elaborate kind of pulleys and gears. So they were
certainly very attuned, especially to think about these mathematical kind of fancy mathematicians
like Thomas and Maxwell. They were very attuned to what we would now call symmetry arguments in
real space, kind of rotate the system around x, y, or z. And so a lot of their models were actually
frankly sort of spherical, like billiard balls or like ball bearings, as opposed to only like
circles. So we'll come to that as well. These are all good questions. Other questions here from the chat?
Or from Dr. Jen. Anyone else have any questions they want to pose for the group?
Feel free to raise, just raise your blue hand at this point too, now that we can see each other.
I like the comment about putting your hand in the jelly now your keyboard sticky. My apologies for
your keyboard, but just trying to catch up on the chat here.
There's a really interesting comment here from Sabrina. I like this. So Sabrina writes that
I don't know what a gun is, a gran unified theory, but it seems like we're moving back
towards everything being the same thing again with the smile emoji. So one of the things that
maybe comes back actually to Iyabo's question. So for some of these folks, the ether was a kind of
word for something that didn't really know what it was. A topic they figured had to be everywhere
because they could infer its effects. If I wiggle something here or something happens there,
there must be some medium that transmitted the influence from A to B. How could a moving bar
magnet possibly affect an electric current because they're both immersed in the shared medium?
It's all pervasive medium. And so they gave it a name. They gave it a name long before they had
any kind of articulated descriptions or analogies. They called it the light bearing ether, luminous
ether decades before they had any kind of more specific ideas about it. And so in that sense,
I think it is kind of like we're in a similar situation today. And we'll talk a bit about this
near the very end of this semester with our quest to understand what's the world made of.
And we have some other, we have very finely articulated models like a standard model and
this kind of neutrino and that kind of electron and up quarks and dow quarks and gluons and Higgs
and all this very specific stuff. And that amounts, as you may know, for not more than five percent
of the kind of mass balance of the universe. We've explained five percent of the universe
with unbelievable precision out to 12 decimal places. Thank you very much. And we know nothing
with a capital N, nothing about the other 95 percent of the mass of the energy balance.
So we give it names. We call it dark matter and dark energy. Again, it will come to in the very
near the end of the very, very end of the term. And I think in some sense, I have some sort of
sympathy with either my present colleagues and myself and or with the kind of people of Faraday's
and Maxwell's age. They didn't know what the ether was, but they knew that had to be there. It was
conveying all these effects. They could measure the effects of disturbing the ether as far as
they were concerned. So they gave it a name, a kind of placeholder name, partly to help organize
their studies. Oh, I'm studying luminiferous ether as well. That helps get scholars on the same page.
They would give their best estimates of what they thought the thing was like and how it behaved,
but they didn't know. They had better or less well compelling responses. And I think we're
in a very similar situation today, not by design, not by our hopes, because we have been stymied
now for four decades to get any more kind of carefully articulated knowledge about what
specifically is dark matter that seems to be filling every galaxy much, much more so than
ordinary matter. And what particularly is this other separate kind of stuff that we now call dark
energy. So I think we again, I don't want to say we've learned nothing since 1820. We can see some
maybe humbling, humility inducing parallels between our best efforts today and the efforts of
very, very earnest, talented folks from long ago. That's a great. So again, we'll keep that in mind
as we as we march forward throughout the term. Julian asks, why are they so reluctant to accept
action at a distance? And how did we come to accept it? Oh, good. Let me take the first one first.
Action at a distance. That's a great topic. Newton famously says, when it comes to the
phenomenon of gravity, I feign no hypothesis. Hypothesis non-fingo is the Latin. He says,
I think that quantitatively, the effect of one mass exerting a force the other goes as the product
of the masses divided by the square of their distance is law of universal gravitation.
What's the underlying reason for that? He says, for that, I feign no hypothesis. He actually had a
lot of hypotheses. He just knew not to write them down. A lot of scholars have argued that he was
actually convinced, at least by analogy, that gravity was a kind of alchemical effect, even
at a time when alchemy was in kind of poor repute. So he said outwardly and publicly,
I don't know what it is, but he seems to have at least been inspired in part by these very,
what we would now call occult forces where something can somehow have an influence on
something else instantly across time and space. So Newton was kind of comfortable with the notion
of action or distance that somehow the earth could instantly tug on the moon and vice versa
without having to wait for some influence to travel, as you hear in there. That, even in its day,
was criticized by a number of scholars, even in Newton's own day, because they thought it did
sound occult. It sounds like, you know, kind of witchcraft. How could this thing possibly affect
something over there? If everything else I see, you know, I throw a pond, excuse me, a rock into
the pond, I see ripples spread out. The distant edges of the pond aren't affected by my rock until
the ripples get there. There were all kinds of common sense observations that suggested to people
like Leibniz, I mean, like Newton's very smart contemporaries, that the physical world seemed
to convey influences by requiring some time for influence to travel from A to B. So Newton's action
or distance was already at least had a kind of curious, you know, kind of bad reputation among
the savants who cared. And then you get to someone like Faraday and Ersted and Thomas Young,
and now they figure they have a reason to finally give up or to finally reject that action or distance
because they have separate reasons based on this wave theory of light, say, oh, there is a seat,
there's a physical explanation available to us for how all these physical phenomena are transmitted
from A to B across space. They're all sitting in this elastic medium, this ether, and that can have
a local disturbance that propagates. So there was, so to speak, an added reason to pile on
and say not only did people wonder about Newton's action or distance in Newton's own day,
now roughly 100, 110 years later, we have new inputs, we have new evidence from our investigations
that suggest something that Newton hadn't known about it or hadn't taken into account at all.
All the more reason to try to find out a kind of local causes yield local effects kind of response.
So that starts getting more and more compelling to this next generation. Now Julian asks, because
he knows what's coming, why do we now accept action or distance? We sort of do and don't,
we have a love-hating relationship with it. I assume Julian that you're referring to quantum
entanglement, your so-called quantum non-locality. If you're not referring to that, I'm going to
hijack this and I'm going to talk about it because I just love it. So we're going to talk about that
actually in a few classes a little bit later this term. So how have we made our kind of
awkward peace with a very certain kind of action or distance not easily, not right away, thanks to
a lot of hard and contested thinking. That's a preview for lecture 12, I think. So we're going to
talk about quantum non-locality. This is one of my favorite topics in the universe. So we'll get to
that too. But for a long, long time between, let's say, you know, 1800 and the 1960s or 70s,
people were quite content to say that action or distance is always, always bad. We never want it.
We never want it in our physics. And they had a range of reasons why they thought that was going
to be an acceptable approach. Aidan asks, how accessible were the lectures and later universities
of research? I mentioned that Faraday did not have much money when he was younger,
but he was the exception. Was the exception to the rule? Did class discrimination preventable? Oh,
yeah, very good. So in Britain, in British history, I mean, the rough shorthand is we're always talking
about class discrimination. So including in Faraday's time. Faraday was absolutely the exception
who proved the rule. It was, as I say, this rags to riches story. It wasn't that there was no social
mobility. And you can read any kind of Charles Dickens novel to see some characters who have a
breakthrough and rise above their station in the language of the time. But in the natural
philosophy, Faraday stands out as a pretty unusual case. And the universities as well, there were
scholarship students at places like Cambridge than is now. So it wasn't only very, very rich
children and very rich families who could go to university, but it was tilted very strongly that
way. And in fact, it's only in Britain in the middle decades of the 20th century, like 100 years
after the days of Thompson and Maxwell, was a very large university reform throughout Britain
to make much more accessible, you know, colleges, universities for many, many more for people from
many more backgrounds, that kind of large scale national university reform comes really in earnest
like 100 years later. So there were students on fellowship. In fact, Isaac Newton was a
scholarship student when he went to Cambridge in his own lifetime in the 1600s. Often they would
have to be basically like a butler or or a maid for their for their roommates, not an ideal
situation, right? This was not like work study. It was like, you have to go clean up for your
rich roommate, not what I recommended. So there were ways to be a student as some of these elite
British universities from from more humble backgrounds, not great. This was well outside
the reach of someone like Faraday. So it does again, the ladder didn't extend sort of arbitrarily low.
But there were there was a range of social classes and universities in this time, not
not a full range. And that begins to change pretty slowly all over the world, including in
Britain, including frankly, the United States. And of course, we still have challenges even here.
So that's a great question. Faraday was indeed the exception who who proves the rule within
natural philosophy. Yeah, great question. Any other questions there? If not, I realize we're
pretty much at the hour. Those are great questions. Thank you so much. I hope it's not too clunky.
We'll try to get better. I'll try to get better at flowing in the questions and discussions
throughout these Zoom lectures. Anyway, thanks, everyone. Great, great questions. I'll post the
video as soon as it's done processing, it'll go to the canvas site, and we'll pick it up there
for next week. Everyone stay well. See you soon.